<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The line of true judgment: laid to an imperfect piece published by Thomas Collier, which he calls An answer to an epistle written to the churches of the Anabaptists, &amp;c. : A reply herein is published in order to the exaltation of the spiritual man, with his ordinances and administrations, above the man of sin, with the weak and unprofitable ordices [sic] that doth not make the comers thereunto perfect. / By Thomas Salthouse.</title>
            <author>Salthouse, Thomas, 1630-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05933</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S474</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R183214</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">49520977</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 49520977</idno>
            <idno type="VID">174207</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05933)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 174207)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2676:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The line of true judgment: laid to an imperfect piece published by Thomas Collier, which he calls An answer to an epistle written to the churches of the Anabaptists, &amp;c. : A reply herein is published in order to the exaltation of the spiritual man, with his ordinances and administrations, above the man of sin, with the weak and unprofitable ordices [sic] that doth not make the comers thereunto perfect. / By Thomas Salthouse.</title>
                  <author>Salthouse, Thomas, 1630-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Simmons ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1658]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>2000 microform ed. lacks p. 21-24.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Friends' Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Collier, Thomas, fl. 1691. --  Answer to an epistle written to the churches of the Anabaptists, &amp;c.</term>
               <term>Salthouse, Thomas, 1630-1691. --  Epistle to the churches of the Anabaptists so called.</term>
               <term>Answer to an epistle written to the churches of the Anabaptists, &amp;c.</term>
               <term>Epistle to the churches of the Anabaptists so called.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anabaptists --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:174207:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:174207:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LINE OF TRUE JUDGMENT: Laid to an imperfect piece publiſhed By <hi>Thomas Collier,</hi> which he calls an Anſwer to an Epiſtle written to the Churches of the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>A Reply herein is publiſhed in order to the Exaltation of the ſpiritual man, with his Ordinances and Adminiſtrations, above the man of ſin, with the weak and unprofitable Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that doth not make the comers thereunto perfect.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>Thomas Salthouſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Behold ye deſpiſers and wonder and periſh, for I work a work in your dayes, a work which ye ſhall in no wiſe believe, though a man declare it unto you,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Acts 13.41.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore they ſay unto God, depart from us, for we deſire not the knowledge of thy wayes,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Job 21.14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>They are of thoſe that rebell againſt the light, they know not the wayes thereof, nor abide in the pathes thereof,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Job 24.13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Simmons,</hi> at the Bull and Mouth near <hi>Alderſgate.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:174207:2"/>
            <p>THe Reader may here obſerve, that the firſt entrance into this diſcourſe, was occaſioned by a printed Paper from <hi>Tiverton;</hi> wherein the ſtate and condition, of the Anabaptiſts Churches was repreſented, which came to my hand; and after I had read it over and conſidered their condition to be far ſhort of what they profeſs, I was moved to write an Epiſtle to them, and ſent it among them, for the better information of the honeſt hearted, and for the ſake of ſuch as are not altogether ſettled upon the lees; and as an anſwer to that Epiſtle, <hi>Thomas Collier</hi> hath written a Pamphlet to vinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate their practiſe and preſent condition, ſhewing them many exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and inſtances of the Saints failings in former ages tending to their incouragment in the estate of ſin and imperfection; intimating that notwithſtanding their great abominations therein expreſſed, they are, and may be owned as the Church of God, in perſuance where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I was constrained to ſend this reply, as a farther manifeſtation of the good will of him that would have all men to be ſaved, and come to the knowledge of the truth, with a ſeaſonable word written by <hi>J.C.</hi> added hereunto, which may go abroad among them to be read, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and conſidered of by ſuch as have not refuſed to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:174207:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The line of true Judgement, laid to an imperfect piece publiſhed by <hi>Thomas Collier,</hi> which he calls an Anſwer to an Epiſtle written to the Churches of the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I conſider the groſs darknes degeneration and Apoſtacy of ſome high pretenders to Religion: and how willfully ignorant they are become of the great miſtery of Godlineſs
<note n="b" place="margin">1 Tim 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> not liking to retain God in their knowledge, nor to hearken to the reproofs of inſtruction, which is the way of eternal life. I remember what the ſpirit hath expreſly ſpoken concerning ſuch
<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 1.28.</note> that in the latter times ſome ſhall depart from the faith; giving heed to ſeducing ſpirits and Doctrines of Divels; ſpeaking lies in hypocriſie, having their conſciences ſeared as with an hot Iron; making Shipwrack of the myſtery of faith
<note n="d" place="margin">1 Tim. 4.</note> which is held in a pure conſcience, and which was once deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered unto the Saints which purifies the heart and gives victory over the world, and after a diligent ſearch and examination had, who it is that are given up to ſtrong deluſions to believe lies, and who teacheth for doctrines the traditions of men;
<note n="e" place="margin">1 Tim 3.9.</note> creeping into houſes; and leading about ſilly women Captive, Laden with ſin, and led away with divers luſts, ever learning, and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth, nor to perfection; I find by evident teſtimony, that the people cal'd Anabaptiſts are as chiefly concerned herein as many of thoſe whom they themſelves have formerly pretended to differ from and declare againſt as Ante-Chriſtian both in call, practice, maintainance, doctrine and worſhip, with whom they are
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:174207:3"/>joyned and confederate to fight againſt the truth as it is in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, as by their practice and the writings of ſome of them is plainly and clearly made manifeſt; for, with the light of Chriſt are they ſeen through their unrighteous covering and feigned humility: and with the Spirit of truth are they tryed, their lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage bewrayes them
<note n="f" place="margin">Eph. 2.12.</note> to be ſtrangers to the Covenant of promiſe, yea ſuch as cannot indure ſound doctrine, nor receive the things of the ſpirit of God, when in the fear of God freely tendered and offered unto them.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as <hi>Thomas Collier</hi> a Teacher among them hath ſeveral times ingaged himſelf, with the beaſt and falſe Prophet to make war againſt the Lamb and his followers; by publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his own imaginations to render them odious to the world, Suggeſting their way and worſhip of the true God, to be hereſy and errour, as his forefathers in all ages have done: and now once more under pretence of Anſwering an Epiſtle of mine written in the fear of God, and ſent to them in love, he hath manifeſted much folly, enmity, ignorance, and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by wreſting and perverting the words of truth and ſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs therein contained, as he hath done, and doth
<note n="g" place="margin">2 Pet. 3.16.</note> the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of truth to his own deſtruction, that he may not be exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his wickedneſs; and ſo proceed further to boaſt of what he hath done herein or heretofore againſt the truth and the faithful witneſſes of it.</p>
            <p>I am conſtrained for the vindication of the truth in general, whereof I am a witneſs, and for which I ſuffer, a little farther to ſearch into his works of darkneſs, that his covering may be ſtript off, and his refuge of lies ſwept away, that he may ſtand naked and bare in the preſence
<note place="margin">Dan. 7.9.</note> of the ancient of dayes before whom the matter in controverſie is to be debated; and as for what I wrote in that Epiſtle, and do write on this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, it is commended to that of God in the conſcience of all ſuch as are ſimple hearted and ſober minded to be read and received without prejudice, either againſt the truth which is reproached by the world, or againſt the earthen veſſel which is herein imployed as an inſtrument; and who hath without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice againſt any particular perſon (though occaſion was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to mention him) made theſe things publique in perſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:174207:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>of a pamphlet lately publiſhed by <hi>T. C.</hi> called an anſwer to an Epiſtle written by me, to the Churches of the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts ſo called.</p>
            <p>When his pretended anſwer was brought to light, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berately ſearcht through, and weighed in an equal ballance, the ſcope of his diſcourſe and weight of his arguments was firſt to prove that <hi>they might be the Church of God, notwithſtanding their great abominations and wickedneſs</hi> confeſſed in their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle from <hi>Tiverton,</hi> with ſeveral inſtances and agravations of the failings of thoſe in former ages whom the Lord ſent his true Prophets and Miniſters to declare againſt, and to call to repentance; and hereby he would imply that the Churches of God in former ages have been ſinful and wicked like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; who profeſs and would be accounted the Church of Chriſt in theſe dayes though imperfect;</p>
            <p>Secondly, Againſt the being of the ſeed of God and light of Chriſt within men, thirdly againſt the Saints attaining to perfection and freedom from ſin whilſt in this mortal eſtate which is the very end for which Chriſt Jeſus gave gifts unto his Miniſters, ordaining ſome to be Prophets, ſome Apoſtles, ſome Paſtors, and ſome Teachers, for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtery, for the edifying of the ſpiritual body till we all come in the unity of the faith unto a perfect man in Chriſt Jeſus, in whom the whole building fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly framed together groweth to an holy temple in the Lord, and the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>know you not that your bodies are the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the holy Ghoſt,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.17.</note> and if any man defile the temple of God, him will God deſtroy,
<note n="k" place="margin">1 Theſ. 1.1.</note> and the Church is in God the Father and in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, where nothing that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean can enter, and the tabernacle of God is with men, as he hath ſaid: I'le walk in them and dwell in them, though <hi>T C.</hi> have affirmed that <hi>God never had yet a Church in the world free from ſin,</hi> and ſo hath laid ſin to the charge of Gods Elect, for
<note n="l" place="margin">John 3.8.</note> he that commits ſin is of the Devil and a ſervant of ſin, and ſo free from righteouſneſs, and this is the cauſe he hath undertaken to plead.</p>
            <p>In the front or enterance into his paper, he hath cited this Scripture, <hi>to the Law and to the teſtimony,</hi> if any ſpeak not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:174207:4"/>to this rule, it is becauſe there is no light in them. Now in regard he hath put in his declaration, and goes about to plead a title or propriety, that the man of ſin hath and muſt have in the Church of Chriſt whilſt here on earth, and hath here cited the Law and Teſtimony (which I own) for a rule to try by; I am conſtrained as Defendant, to join iſſue and plead with him, according to the Law of Truth, in the preſence of our Judge and Law-giver, whoſe judgement is true, and whoſe teſtimony is ſure.</p>
            <p>But firſt it is to be conſidered, what the Law and what the Teſtimony is, and where they are according to the Scripture; <hi>Thy law is light,</hi> Prov. 6. <hi>The law is ſpiritual,</hi> Rom 7.14. <hi>The law gives the knowledge of ſin,</hi> Rom. 3 20. <hi>And behold the daye come, ſaith the Lord,</hi> Jer. 31. <hi>that I will make a new Covenant with the houſe of Iſrael, and with the houſe of Judah, not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Covenant that I made with their fathers; which Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant they break, but this ſhall be the Covenant that I will make with them after thoſe dayes: I will put my law in their inward parts, and write it in their hearts;</hi> And again, Heb. 10. <hi>I will put my laws in their hearts, and in their minds will I write them, and their ſins and iniquities will I remember no more;</hi> and this is the Covenant that makes the comers thereunto perfect, and the Law which makes free from the law of ſin and death; and he that believeth hath this witneſs in himſelf, and ſo hath ſet to his ſeal that God is true, and the teſtimony of Jeſus is the ſpirit of propheſie; and this is that ſure word ſpoken of 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. <hi>And we have alſo a more ſure word of propheſie where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ye do well that ye take heed as unto a light that ſhineth in a dark place, until the day dawn, and the day ſtar ariſe in your hearts;</hi> (mark) In your hearts: the Law in the heart, the light in the heart, the teſtimony of Jeſus, the ſure word of propheſie in the heart, the word of faith nigh in the heart. And now to come to the matter, he ſaith, pag. 2. <hi>Chriſt was ſent to ſave his people, and not to ſave onely the oppreſſed ſeed or light within;</hi> to which I ſay, he was ſent to ſet the oppreſſed free, and to ſave his people from their ſins, and to open the eyes of the blind,
<note n="m" place="margin">John. 9.39.</note> that thoſe that ſaw not might ſee,
<note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 18.11.</note> and the ſon of man was ſent to ſeek and to ſave that which was loſt, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:174207:4"/>the Lord of hoſts hath left us a ſeed, elſe
<note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 9.</note> we had been as <hi>Sodome,</hi> yea, like unto <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> and this ſeed is <hi>within:</hi> and we know that the whole Creation travelleth together in pain until now, and not onely they but our ſelves alſo that have the firſt fruits of the ſpirit, even we our ſelves have groaned within our ſelves, for the redemption of the body which God hath prepared to do his will,
<note n="p" place="margin">1 Cor. 15,</note> who giveth unto every ſeed its own body, and he that is begotten of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal ſeed, and born again of water and of the ſpirit, is ſaved from his ſin, and he ſinneth not, neither can he, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſeed of God remaineth in him, and he cannot ſin becauſe he is born of God, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. Mark, he cannot ſin, becauſe he is born of God, and becauſe the ſeed remaineth <hi>in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>T.C.</hi> ſaith pages 2, 3. <hi>It is language beſides the Goſpel of truth, that Chriſt came to ſave the oppreſſed ſeed within;</hi> and farther, that he dare ſay, <hi>it is ſuch a ſalvation as never came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the heart of God, nor was ever known to Prophets, Apoſtles, or Chriſt himſelf to ſave the oppreſſed ſeed of God in men, with which his Covenant is made.</hi> Here he hath contradicted the Scriptures of truth above-mentioned, with many others that might be inſtanced; likewiſe he hath contradicted himſelf, for he with others of his brethren, directs their Epiſtle from <hi>Tiver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> to ſuch as are called to be Saints, through the immortal ſeed which dwelleth in them: now if it be language beſides the Goſpel of truth, to mention the oppreſſed ſeed within; why doth he make uſe of the expreſſion? and if it be accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to truth, why doth he ſuggeſt that thoſe who uſe ſuch expreſſions, are poor deluded people? and becauſe I ſaid in the beginning of my Epiſtle to them, I am conſtrained with compaſſion to the oppreſſed ſeed in you, which groans to be delivered from the bondage of corruption, &amp;c. he ſeems to render it an offence by falſe conſtructions, ariſing from an evil affected mind, wreſting and perverting my words, and then calling it a mear cheat to pleaſe children and ſools, as if it were a language not fit to be ſpoken of, or once named among them that are grown ſo ſtrong in the ſtate of imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:174207:5"/>And becauſe my Epiſtle was directed to the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts Churches ſo called, and then I denied them to be the Church of Chriſt, and told them that their preſumption was ſeen that called themſelves the Church of Chriſt and were not, as their blaſphemy was known that called themſelves
<note n="q" place="margin">Rev. 2 9.</note> Jews and were not. He calls this contradiction and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but the confuſion is in himſelf, as may appear to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Reader of that Epiſtle. And this I ſay farther, that although they be called, and calls themſelves the Church, yet were they never owned, nor by me called the Church of Chriſt; for as I ſaid before, the Church of Chriſt is as a Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly among thorns in relation to their condition, expreſſed and confeſſed under their hands in print; and it ſeems they have refuſed to return from their wickedneſs and great abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, if this man may be credited in what he writes concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them, page 8. where he denies not, but they are guilty of thoſe ſins expreſſed and confeſſed in their Epiſtle from <hi>Tiverton;</hi> but ſaith, <hi>He truſts they ſhall be found ſo more, if this be to be vile, we ſhall yet be more vile.</hi> Now how can they be more vile then they have rendred themſelves in that one Epiſtle? where they confeſs they have been drawing iniquity with cords of vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſlaviſh fear hath ſtopt their mouths, till the mouth of this iniquity hath almoſt devoured their poor Churches, &amp;c. and that their affections to Chriſt are alienated, and that the world like a Canker hath eaten out their time, their ſtrength, their zeal, and that the Kingdoms of the world hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched them, ſo that they are become cruel to ſervants and children, exacting all their labours, with many other offences by them confeſſed, which may ſeem to render them vile and uncomely, both in the ſight of God and men, and yet he is ſo impudent as to ſay, <hi>if this be to be vile, I trust we ſhall be more vile.</hi> Let him that hath moderation judge if this be not to glory in their ſhame, yet they pretend after all this, to take ſome effectual courſe (as they ſay) to purge away ſin, and ſinners out of the houſe of God, which if they do, not one of them will be left, but to them it ſeems unpoſſible to purge away ſin and ſinners, if it be true, which is here affirmed by <hi>T.C.</hi> pag. 7. <hi>they that ſay they are without ſin in this mortal eſtate,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:174207:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>they are none of the Church of Chriſt:</hi> and after he hath revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt what I wrote, concerning the baptiſm that now ſaveth, and the great ſalvation that is begun to be ſpoken of, he confeſſeth it to be a bleſſed truth, and then ſaith, <hi>it is ſuch a ſalvation as never entred into the heart of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Should I but ſearch through his writings, and ſet it in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der before him, contradiction and confuſion would appear eminently therein, but that is not my work nor intention; neither ſhall I render unto him or any other evil for evil, and railing for railing, nor make him an offender for a word, nor contend and ſtrive about words, for I have not ſo learned Chriſt; and this I know, that there is a witneſs for God in many of them, that ſhall confeſs to the truth of what is by me written, and it ſhall ſtand upon true record for ever, though at preſent he loves not holy things, nor cannot receive pearls, but turns again to tear and rend him that freely offers them, to ſuch as are covering after the beſt things. But now we ſhall proceed to his doctrine in oppoſition to perfection, and the Saints freedom from ſin, to which I am called, and conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make defence for the truths vindication, as the ſpirit gives utterance, and firſt to what he affirms pag. 5. <hi>Now to this I ſay firſt as concerning the Church or Churches of Chriſt, that God never had a Church in the world free from ſin, nor were there any durſt ſo to ſay, except the Phariſees and Hypocrites, the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers excepted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh, from whence is this man fallen? and what is become of all thoſe deſires and preſſing after perfection that once ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in him? ſee his general Epiſtle to the univerſal Church; doth he (and his followers) now think to be made perfect in the fleſh, that have made ſo fair a ſhew of beginning in the ſpirit, and ſuch large pretences of holineſs as he hath done? how hath he mingled himſelf among the diſhonourable veſſels of iron and clay, the very feet of the Image? what damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble doctrine is this, that he holds forth in behalf of the Prince of darkneſs? Surely this will pleaſe the man of ſin well, to let him be exalted above all that is called God, &amp; to plead his cauſe and intereſt in the Church of Chriſt, to exerciſe Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip over Gods heritage, whilſt here on earth, for <hi>Sions</hi> ſake I
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:174207:6"/>can no longer hold in; for if we ſhould keep ſilence that are called to contend for the faith which purifies the heart, and hear the name of God and his doctrine blaſphemed, the ſtones out of the wall, and beam out of the timber would cry out againſt this wickedneſs, to ſay that God never had a Church here on earth free from ſin. This renders the
<note n="r" place="margin">Eph. 1.22, 23</note> body of Chriſt not to be without ſin; but let <hi>T. C.</hi> know (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he affirm to the contrary) that the Lord hath reſerved ſeven thouſand in <hi>England</hi> that hath not received the mark of the Beaſt in their fore heads, nor in their right hands, nor bowed to his Image, nor defiled themſelves with women, nor with the pollutions of Idols; beſides, a cloud of witneſſes wherewith we are compaſſed about, that in their generation fulfilled the will of God, and walked before him with an upright heart, as doth at large appear in the declaration of truth, which agrees to the exhortation of Chriſt, and the gifts given unto men by Chriſt, who ſaid, <hi>be ye perfect, even as your heavenly father is perfect,</hi> Mat. 5.48. <hi>who alſo aſcended up on high, led captivity captive, and gave gifts unto men, for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry, till we all come in the unity of the faith, unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt,</hi> Eph. 4. <hi>And the Miniſter of Chriſt whoſe preachng was not with excellency of ſpeech, nor with the enticing words of mens wiſdom, but in the demonſtration of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and of power;</hi> he ſaith of himſelf, and his fellow la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers
<note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.</note> 
               <hi>we ſpeak wiſdom among them that are perfect,</hi> and their preaching was to the Churches of Chriſt, whilſt in the world, though it is here affirmed that God never had a Church in the world free from ſin, nor none that ever durſt ſo to ſay, except Phariſees and Hypocrites.</p>
            <p>And yet the Apoſtle ſaith concerning himſelf and the Church; <hi>how ſhall we that are dead to ſin live any longer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, for ſin ſhall not have dominion over you, for ye are not under the Law, but under Grace, being then made free from ſin ye became the ſervants of righteouſneſs,</hi> Rom. 6.
<note n="t" place="margin">Col. 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>and ye are compleat in him, who is the head of all principalities and powers, in whom ye are circumciſed with the circumciſion made without hands, in putting off the body of the ſins of the fleſh, by the circumciſion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:174207:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Chriſt; buried with him in Baptiſme, wherein alſo you were raiſed with him through the faith of the operation of God, who hath raiſed him from the dead;</hi> and
<note n="u" place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Therefore we are buried with him by Baptiſme into Death; that like as Chriſt was raiſed from the Dead by the glory of the Father, even ſo we alſo ſhould walke in newneſs of life:</hi> and as hee is, ſo are we in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. and the Church of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> was come
<note n="w" place="margin">Heb. 12.23</note> to the Spirits of Juſt men made perfect; and they who teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied theſe things, was not hypocrits as in this mans account; and now I leave it to the ſpirituall mans judgment; whether ever God had a Church in this world free from ſin; or any that durſt confeſs it; yea, or nay; and farther hee affirmes pag. 7. that <hi>they that calls themſelves the Church of Chriſt, and ſay they are without ſin in this mortall Eſtate, are none of the Church of Chriſt; for he had never yet any ſuch Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I ſay, his judgment is falſe and denyed, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared againſt by the children of light, and witneſſed againſt by the Scripture of truth; for the Life of Chriſt hath been, and is made manifeſt in mortall fleſh; and
<note n="x" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.7.</note> we have this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in harth en veſſels; and for this purpoſe was the ſon of God made manifeſt to take away ſin:
<note n="y" place="margin">1 Joh. 4.3.</note> and every Spirit that Confeſſeth not that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh is not of God; and this is that Spirit of Anti-Chriſt that now is in the world; but where Jeſus Chriſt is made manifeſt in the fleſh, hee is made manifeſt to Deſtroy the works of the Devill, to wit ſin; and to condemn ſin in the fleſh, that the Righteouſneſs of the Law might be fulfilled <hi>In us</hi> who walks not after the fleſh but after the Spirit; being Created a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain
<note n="z" place="margin">Eph. 2.10.</note> in Chriſt Jeſus unto good works
<note n="a" place="margin">Coll. 1.4.</note> in whom we have Redemption through his blood; who hath purged away our ſins, by the waſhing of Regeneration; glory to his name for ever; without boaſting we can ſpeak it to the praiſe of his grace, who hath wrought all our works for us and <hi>In us:</hi> that
<note n="b" place="margin">1 Joh. 5.19.</note> wee are of God though the whole world lieth in wickedneſs; and that Chriſt have had and yet hath a Church without ſin in this mortall Eſtate; for hee that ſinneth hath not ſeene God neither known him: and we deny all ſuch to be the Church of God, and of Chriſt as lives in ſin, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:174207:7"/>pleads for ſin, whilſt in this mortall Eſtate who makes a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Scriptures and comes not to the Life and power declared of by them.</p>
            <p>For the Scripture we own and the Covenant which makes the comers thereunto perfect, and the bringing in of a better hope we witneſſe, and the Law which makes free
<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 8.2.</note> from the Law of ſin and death; and the unchangable ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Adminiſtrations to which we are ſubject, doth not periſh with the uſing; and the Baptiſme by which wee are made members of the Church of Chriſt doth not De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, but increaſe and ſave from ſin: and all ſuch as are called Churches and yet remains in ſin, in the uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted and Imperfect Eſtate, offends in many things, and are ſeduced and deceived, being out of the truth, they are eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the Croſs of Chriſt in the ſtrife and envy againſt truth; and theſe are not the Church of Chriſt, neither do they know it, but are ſtrangers to the ſaints Life, having a like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a thing, a forme of godlineſs, but not the power,
<note n="d" place="margin">Rev. 3.1.</note> a name to live and are dead; and with ſuch we have no union; knowing them by their voice to be ſtrangers; and therefore wee turne away from them; and cannot but deale plainely and faithfully with them, though we bee reproched by them with the name of Quakers, and joyned with Phariſees and Hypocrites, becauſe we cannot conforme to the cuſtoms of the Heathen, and plead (as they do) for the Devills kingdom of ſin and Imperfection, that Anti-Chriſt may have quiet poſſeſſion in the Church of Chriſt ſo long as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines here in the world.</p>
            <p>And becauſe we cannot own them as Miniſters and Elders of the Church of Chriſt that ſometimes murmurs and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines of the tyrannicall government of the man of ſin in them, but pleades for the continuance of ſin in the Church whilſt in this mortall Eſtate; therefore hee concludes that we are not ſenſible of ſin in our ſelves nor in others, as to warn them to mourn and ſeek the Lord for them.</p>
            <p>To which I ſay we all like ſheep have gone a ſtray, and in ſin we were conceived, and in iniquity brought forth, and were by nature the children of wrath even as others, till it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:174207:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>pleaſed the father in the riches of his grace and love, to reveal his Son in us; to deſtroy the works of the Divell, and to condemen ſin in the fleſh; and by his blood to cleanſe us from all ſin, and we have known the terrours of the Lord, and his indignation againſt ſin, and have been made ſenſible of our condition, whilſt ſin reigned in our mortall Bodies; and wee have mourned under it every familie apart, when by the light of Chriſt it was made manifeſt, and by faith in him many have obtained victory over the ſin that did eaſly beſet us and lead us captive; and how can we that are dead to ſin live any longer therein; <hi>ſhall we continue in ſin</hi> (and plead for ſo doing like you) <hi>that grace may abound, nay, God forbid</hi> that any ſuch thoughts ſhould enter into our hearts, to draw us back to the pollutions which we have eſcaped, and with the dog to the vomet, and the ſow that was waſhed, to her wallowing in the mire again; nay verily we are ſneſible of that condition, and cannot but warn them that yet remains in it, and exhort them to come forth of it; and we do pitty them, and pray for them that they may be delivered from the bondage of corruption, and out of the ſnares of the enemie; and turned from the darkneſs to the light, that as obedient children, they may come to walk honeſtly as in the day in the light of the Lord; and to this end do we labour and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile, and freely adminiſter as we have received, commending our ſelves to that of God in every mans conſcience; again hee ſaith, pag. 9. <hi>let both heaven and earth tremble at ſuch rebellion and pride as this is;</hi> Intimating that we Judge and Condemn all that dare not walk in ſuch a way of diſobedience, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Hear I appeal to all ſober minded people, that ever heard us ſpeak, or read our writings; whether ever we judged or condemned any that was obedient t othe faith; or when did we ever preſs any to diſobedience, or did in the leaſt countenance it; but have often declared that the wrath of God cometh upon the children of diſobedience; and ſurely if this man had not a face harder then a flint, I believe ſhame would ſtrike him in the face, at the reading again, in the cool of the day, what hee hath forged againſt us in the heat and bitterneſs of his Spirit; for all that have heard us will be ready with one conſent to ſay, that we preſs moſt after obedience,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:174207:8"/>of any other profeſſion or people whatſoever, and we have ſure ground for ſo doing: knowing that the promiſe of the Lord and his bleſſing is to the obedient: and that the terrors of the Lord, and his wrath is againſt the
<note n="e" place="margin">Col. 3.6.</note> children of diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; and our teſtimony ſtands upon record againſt all ſuch as
<note n="f" place="margin">Job. 24.13.</note> rebells againſt the light, and againſt all who are proud, heady and <hi>high minded, Diſobedient to parents, without natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall affection,</hi> ſuch as are
<note n="g" place="margin">Gal. 3.1.</note> bewitched and doth not obey the truth as it is in Jeſus.</p>
            <p>And to ſay that wee walk in a way of diſobedience is ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly falſe: for our way is the good old way of holineſs. Jeſus Chriſt who ſaith I am the light of the world, and
<note n="h" place="margin">John. 8.12.</note> he that followeth me ſhall not abide in darkneſs, but ſhall have the light of life, and his record is true, and we have believed it; and again, he ſaith
<note n="i" place="margin">John. 14.6.</note> I am the way, and no man cometh to the father but by me; and of this way we bear teſtimony, and in this way we walk, and whoſoever ſaith they believe in Chriſt, and followes Chriſt, and doth not believe in the light, and walk in obedience to the light, are deceived and led aſide with the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the wicked, and are in the rebellion and diſobedience, and ſuch with the light are judged and
<note n="k" place="margin">John. 3.19.</note> condemned, and by us declared againſt in that eſtate of diſobedience; yet we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ceaſe to call them to repentance, that if peradventure they may come to the knowledge of the truth: but he ſaith pag. 11. <hi>that they endeavour to turn ſouls from Chriſt to the light within them, teaching abſolute diſobedience and rebellion againſt Chriſt in his word the Scriptures; and obedience to their own fancies; and lying imaginations within them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I ſay; this is but his own falſe conſtruction and vain imaginations mixt with Ignorance and enmity; for the Scripture is a witneſs with us of what we teach and of what we believe; and endeavour to turn people unto, and he might as well have accuſed the Miniſters of Chriſt as us in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; for they were ſent
<note n="l" place="margin">Acts. 26.18.</note> to turn people from the darkneſs to the light; and in ſo doing, neither they nor we did nor doth endeavour to turn them to fancies; nor teach them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt Chriſt in his word, this is but the poyſon of Aſps that cometh from under his tongue; and we can bear it;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:174207:8"/>being exerciſed with the reproaches of <hi>Moab,</hi> and the revile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Children of <hi>Ammon,</hi> with whom this man hath joyned himſelf to fight againſt the truth; yet notwithſtanding for the truths defence and vindication, this may inform the ſimple hearted, that are not come to a right underſtanding of what we hold and teach, that we do not endeavour to turn ſouls to a light within them diſtinct from Chriſt; but we la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to turn people to the true light of Chriſt <hi>in them;</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.6.</note> for God who commanded the light to ſhine out of darkneſs hath ſhined in our hearts; and this is the true light which we have ſeen and which we declare, and endeavour to turn people to, and this is the light which <hi>John</hi> was ſent to bear witneſs of, <hi>that all men through him might believe
<note n="n" place="margin">John. 1.</note> the true light that lighteth every man that cometh into the world:</hi> and this is not a fancy nor an imagination, as is falſly affirmed by <hi>T. C.</hi> who farther pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds to call it a natural light, and the ruins or remainders of that which was in the firſt <hi>Adam;</hi> and ſaith <hi>it is the great deſign of theſe men to ſet it up in oppoſition to the true light and life of Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi> but this alſo is his own blindneſs and ignorance, of what wee labour to ſet up that cauſeth the miſtake and falſe judgement, for we labour to turn people to the true ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual light of the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> who is the Lord from heaven heavenly; that as they have ſinned through one mans diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, they may by the obedience of one be made free from ſin and death; and to this end are we called and ſent forth in the name of the Lord, to call ſinners to repentance that are in the loſt eſtate in the firſt <hi>Adam;</hi> and to turn people from the darkneſs to the true light, that they may come to worſhip the onely true God (whom we worſhip) in the ſpirit and in the truth, and this is the work of our Miniſtery; having turned people from the darkneſs to the light, to ſtir up the pure mind <hi>in them</hi> by daily exhortations and provocations to love and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to him, who hath required truth in the inward parts; that holineſs may be
<note n="o" place="margin">2 COr. 7.1.</note> perfected in the fear of God; that their light (which doth ſhine) may ſhine clearer and clearer before men, that thereby the Lord may be glorified, and the mouths of gain-ſayers ſtopped; and herein have we union with the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of whom the world was not worthy: who ſuſtained the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:174207:9"/>ſame ſufferings, reproaches, and tryals of cruel mockings, bonds and impriſonments (as wee do) for the teſtimony which they held, and by the ſame power are we kept through faith unto ſalvation; ſo that we can rejoyce when men reviles and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutes us for Chriſts ſake and the Goſpel; knowing that if our Goſpel be hid, <hi>it is hid to them that are loſt;
<note n="p" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.3.</note> whoſe minds the God of this world hath blinded,</hi> and whoſe ears with the deaf Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der are ſtopped; that although we ſpeak plainly according to the Scripture, and declare what we have heard and ſeen, yet it cannot be received by ſuch as are given up to believe lies; and truly this man hath manifeſted as much enmity and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance herein againſt us, as if he had ſold himſelf to work wickedneſs, and bent his tongue for lies; he calls them hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid abuſes againſt Chriſt, Scripture and Saints, that I would have the light within, to be believed in and loved, and becauſe I call Chriſt the <hi>true ſeed,</hi> the <hi>true light, the Lord, the Law gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, the more ſure word of Propheſy,</hi> &amp;c. he makes it as ſome hainous offence, and labours to make a ſeparation between Chriſt and his light in the conſciences of men and women, which upon good grounds we exhort people to turn unto, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in, love and obey: for God hath given him for
<note n="q" place="margin">Luk. 2.37.</note> 
               <hi>a light unto the Gentiles, a leader of his people, and for ſalvation to all the ends of the earth, to open the eyes of the blind, and to bring forth the priſoners out of the priſon houſes;</hi> end this is our meſſage to the world to declare
<note n="r" place="margin">1 John. 1.5.</note> that God is <hi>light,</hi> and in him is no dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at all, and to turn people from the darkneſs to this <hi>light,</hi> that they may be brought out of the eſtate of degeneration and imperfection where they have lain covered with groſs darkneſs, feeding themſelves with the hypocrites hope and empty ſhadowes as of a light without; a word with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out; Chriſt without; A Church without; baptiſm without; bread and wine without; ordinances and adminiſtrations all with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out; <hi>which makes not the commers thereunto perfect;</hi> being car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally obſerved according to traditions received from men: and that which moſt agravates their miſery; they are ſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited, and will not hearken to the reproofs of inſtruction, nor receive the things of the Spirit of God when freely tendered and offered without money and without price.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:174207:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> Oh that you did but know the deſires and breathings that proceeds from the ſpirit that <hi>ever lives to make interceſſion unto God for you; why will you ſpend your money for that which is no bread and your labour for that which doth not ſatisfy? how long will you make lies your refuge,</hi> and feed upon aſhes, and cover your ſelves with unrighteous coverings? the flying Angel is gone forth with the everlaſting Goſpel to preach to all nations, kinreds, tongues and languages, and the call hath reached unto you that have been aſleep
<note n="s" place="margin">Dan 12.2.</note> in the duſt of the earth: Therefore harden not your hearts but incline your eares, and hearken dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently what the ſpirits ſaith, and take heed of
<note n="t" place="margin">Heb. 2.</note> neglecting this great ſalvation, for this is the day of your viſitation; and once more a word of exhortation to you as from the Lord to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to
<note n="u" place="margin">Joh. 12.3.</note> the light and believe in the light, and love the light, &amp;c.
<note n="w" place="margin">Rev. 21.2.</note> walke in it that you may have fellowſhip with us, and that you may be received into the generall aſſembly, where the only true God is worſhipped in the ſpirit and truth
<note n="x" place="margin">Pſa. 29.2.</note> in the beauty of holineſs: but he ſaith pag. 13. <hi>we know it is an eaſy thing to be received by them without any letters of recommendation, for if a man will but turn away from Christ, and faith, and ſcriptures, and obedience, and turne to the light within, and ſay he is perfect, and can ſay thee and thou, he may quickly be one of their Church, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But truely he is deceived herein; for its not ſo eaſy to be a member of our Church (which is the true Church) as he ignorantly pretends; though the gates be not at all ſhut by day, yet there can in no wiſe enter <hi>any thing that defileth and is polluted;</hi> nor no <hi>prophane perſon,</hi> neither <hi>whatſoever worketh abomination:
<note n="y" place="margin">Rev. 22.15.</note> for without are dogs, and drunkards, and ſorcerers, and whoremongers, and ſwearers, and murderers, and idolaters, and whoſoever loveth and maketh a lye:</hi> and its death to any beaſt, that comes near the mountain of the Lords houſe, which is eſtabliſhed in the top of all mountains:
<note n="z" place="margin">Iſay. 2.</note> and exalted above the hills, where we <hi>worſhip God in the ſpirit</hi> in the true order and fellowſhip, where all may ſpeak
<note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.</note> one by one as the ſpirit moves and gives utterance; and if any of the adulterated generation ſhould come among us from a far country, and bring a letter of recommendation from ſome great man of the world, or from an aſſembly of profeſſing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:174207:10"/>people; his ſpirit would ſoon be tryed whether he were of God or not; for we cannot
<note n="b" place="margin">Joh. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>believe</hi> nor receive <hi>every ſpirit</hi> that may come with <hi>excellency of ſpeech, and the inticing words of mens wiſdom,</hi> and be commended by men, and paſs for a good Chriſtian in the worlds account; for we know the voice of Chriſt
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h. 10.5.</note> and <hi>ſtrangers we cannot hearken to;</hi> And as for ſuch as turnes away from Chriſt, faith and obedience, they are more like to be received by, and to find acceptance among the Anabaptiſts (then among us) if they will but take up their great ordinance as they call it (to wit) water Baptiſm, the ſecond or third time, and make Confeſſion of their ſins, that light ſpirit, that wretched worldly ſpirit, &amp;c. They muſt be owned as brethren and ſiſters, Chriſts excellent ones, although they be cruell to children and ſervants, mockers of God, &amp;c. See a large deſcription of the Eſtate of their Church in their Epiſtle from <hi>Tiverton,</hi> and look abroad among all profeſſions in the nation, if worſe fruits can be found then is brought forth among them; but how can we expect better till the vineyard be dreſſed by huſbandmen of the Lords cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and ſending; its manifeſt they ran and was not ſent; and therefore the people are not profited by them; and truly its far eaſier to be a member of ſuch an imperfect Church as theirs, the way being ſo wide, then it is to be of ours; for the way is ſtraight that leads to it,
<note n="d" place="margin">Cor. 12.13</note> the Baptiſme being ſpirituall by which they are received in, and <hi>the naturall man cannot receive the things of the ſpirit of God:</hi> and the words <hi>thee</hi> and <hi>thou</hi> doth not make a member of the true Church; neither are they the principle of our Religion, for they may be uſed in the deceipt, as well as the truth may be holden in unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, though they be proper and pure language, and by us uſed and owned, yet let none think that our Religion depends only upon words, but that we are builded upon the ſure foundation of many generations for an habitation of God through the ſpirit
<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ph. 2.20.22</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt Jeſus himſelf being the chief corner ſtone:</hi> and many that pretends to Religion in theſe dayes, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes the ſcripture for a rule, are ſo far from coming to be of our Church, that a word of exhortation can hardly have entrance among them; neither can the ſcripture language be born by <hi>T.C.</hi> and his adherents; for becauſe I ſaid <hi>the Law is
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:174207:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Heb. 7.</note> changed, and the Prieſthood is changed,</hi> and <hi>the Covenant which made not the commers thereunto perfect,</hi> for <hi>the weakneſſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitableneſs of it is done away, &amp;c.</hi> he ſaith, <hi>take theſe words as they are ſtated, and they ſpeak forth moſt horrible iniquity,</hi> though they be ſtated expreſly as they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in Scripture; <hi>and,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the ordinances that we walke in are the new teſtament ordinances groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon the new reſtament Covenant;</hi> but truly its very unlike, ſeeing their Covenant and ordinances doth not make the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers thereunto perfect, which thing he denyes both in Epiſtle and practice, as is plainly manifeſt to the childrne of light; And ſhould I but trace him through his Epiſtle from <hi>Tiverton;</hi> and this imperfect piece written as a vindication of it; and their Churches imperfect Eſtate; a Large volume would but contain the particular circumſtances; but I ſhall refer the reader to that Epiſtle, and mine in perſuance of it, which was not written by me to the intent of ſtrife, or contention about words, but in the feare of the Lord, by way of exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to repentance; after I had deliberatly read over and conſidered the ſtate of their Church under their hands in print, and although I did write in love and tenderneſs, and in plainneſs of ſpeech, and in Engliſh; yet <hi>T. C.</hi> pretends to interpret it, to make it ſpeake another thing then is inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; and when he hath ſet down his own falſe conſtructions and interpretations, he calls it our Logick; and ſo ſports himſelfe in his own deceivings; and then ſaith he, <hi>I trust that every tender and faithfull ſoul, that trembles at the word of the Lord, will tremble at the thoughts of the reception of ſuch divinity as this is:</hi> which is nothing but a falſe divination of his own heart, for thoſe that trembles at the word of the Lord, doth little approve of his divinitie; its more pleaſing among, and more delightful to them that cannot indure ſound Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and they can well agree with, and approve of ſuch teachers as will countenance ſin, and plead for the being and living in ſin, whilſt in this mortall Eſtate.</p>
            <p>But to preſs after holineſs, perfection and obedience to the light of Chriſt <hi>Within,</hi> Oh this is a hard ſaying, the land cannot beare ſuch language; <hi>away with ſuch a fellow, its not fit hee ſhould</hi> breathe in the ayr or live upon the earth: <hi>he brings certain ſtrange things to our eares, this</hi> is <hi>a new Doctrine,</hi> he
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:174207:11"/>us of a light within us, but this is a naturall light (ſay they) this is not the light of Chriſt; for when Chriſt cometh, no man knoweth whence he is, but we know of this light in us; let us heare of ſomething that we know not, and tell not us of a light within us that reproves for ſin, and convinces of ſin; and thus the day of ſmall things is diſpiſed, and the reproofs of inſtruction ſet at nought, and the firſt principle of pure Religion ſlighted as too meane and too low things for ſuch high ſpirits to ſtoop to in theſe dayes.</p>
            <p>And becauſe out of a true ſence of their miſerable Eſtate and condition, expreſſed in their Epiſtle, I ſaid to the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple hearted <hi>come out from among them, and be ye ſeparated,</hi> leaſt you periſh in their gainſaying, he ſaith, <hi>this is the great worke of all, Phariſee-like, to compaſs ſea and land to make one proſelyte;</hi> now let the underſtanding and wiſe hearted judge, if I have offended herein, and whether it be not ſafe to come out from among them that are formall in holy duties, and without the terrour of Gods Majeſty, &amp;c. as they are by their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion.</p>
            <p>Was it Phariſee-like when the true Prophet called to a people to come out from among them that lived in ſin, and not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take with them any longer therein, leaſt they alſo ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of their punniſhment? and is it an offence now, to call the ſimple hearted to come out from among them that lives in ſin, and pleads for the continuance of it? ſo long as they remaine in this world,
<note place="margin">Tim. 35.</note> and the Miniſter of Chriſt ſaith <hi>g</hi> that thoſe who had <hi>the forme of godlineſs,</hi> and <hi>not the power,</hi> was to be turned away from; <hi>for what concord hath Chriſt with Beliall, or what communion hath light with Darkneſſe, or what agreement hath the temple of God with Idolls, for ye are the temple of the living God, as God hath ſaid, I will dwell in them, and walk in them; wherefore come out from among them and be ſeperate, and touch no unclean thing, and I will receive you, and ye ſhall be my ſons and daughters ſaith the Lord Almighty,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. and this was not Phariſee-like to make a proſylite, and, he ſaith, <hi>but why muſt they come out from amongſt us?</hi> to which I ſhall here anſwer in plaine Engliſh, and ſo ſave him labour to interpret; firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have not profited by your Miniſtry, as you Confeſs you have laboured in vain, and that which hath been brought
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:174207:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>forth hath been to little purpoſe: Secondly, becauſe you have
<note n="h" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>the forme of godlineſs and not the power thereof,</hi> and doth impoſe ſuch ordinances upon them, <hi>as doth not make the commers thereunto perfect.</hi> Thirdly becauſe of your coldneſs and deadneſs, that indifferency and <hi>Laodicean</hi> ſpirit that is fallen in upon you: Fourthly, becauſe you have been <hi>drawing iniquity with cords of vanity,</hi> whilſt you have ſaid, <hi>Let the Counſell of the Lord come that we may know it;</hi> in a word, becauſe your Church hath ſin remaining in it, and you believe it will never be otherwiſe whilſt you are in this mortall Eſtate; ſo that your Miniſtry is not <hi>for the perfecting of the ſaints</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Eph. 4.</note> the ends for which Chriſt gave Giftes to his Miniſters; and again he ſaith, <hi>whether muſt they come, doubtleſs to them a pure perfect people without ſin;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay yea, unto a people
<note n="k" place="margin">Deut. 33.29.</note> ſaved by the Lord, ſaved from their ſins, ſaved from the untoward generation, with a great and mighty ſalvation: to ſuch a people are they called to come, to the generally aſſembly, to the Church which is in God; to a pure people,
<note n="l" place="margin">Heb. 12.23.</note> to the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect, that they may be the Lords in the day
<note n="m" place="margin">Mal. 3.7.</note> when he makes up his jewells; for now he is bringing in the deſire of all nations, who ſaith <hi>to the ſea, give up,</hi> and the light is riſen out of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity and we have ſeene it, and now the Lord is gathering his ſeed from the caſt, and from the weſt;
<note n="n" place="margin">I ſay. 43.</note> who ſaith <hi>to the north give up,</hi> and <hi>to the ſouth keep not back, bring my ſons from far, and my daughters from the ends of the earth,</hi> bring forth the blind people that have eyes, and the deaf that have eares, and let the nations be aſſembled, for now is ſalvation and ſtrength come, and we cannot be ſilent, but freely invite and exhort the ſimple hearted to come up with us to the houſe of the Lord.</p>
            <p>And therefore I ſay again,
<note n="o" place="margin">I ſay. 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>Come let us walk in the light of the Lord, come with me from Lebanon; in vain is ſalvation hoped for from the hills, or from the multitude of mountains; ariſe and come away, look from the top of Amana, come from the Lions den, and from the mountains of Leopards, come up out of Egypt and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon, enquire the way to Sion, ſeek the Lord while he may be found, and call upon him while he is near;</hi> come up hither to worſhip God in the ſpirit and in the truth, and ſeek not the living among the dead,
<note n="p" place="margin">Rev. 22.17.</note> 
               <hi>The ſpirit and the bride ſaith come, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:174207:12"/>whoſoever will come, let him come to the waters freely, and drink without money and without price.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This word is to you that are athirſt, and to you that are tender-hearted in plainneſs to your underſtandings (and not the voice of a ſtrange women) therefore hearken diligently, and be not as the untamed Heifer, ſtuffing up and feeding up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wind; come off the barren mountains, where you have been wandering in the cloudy and dark day, and turn to the light of Chriſt Jeſus (in all your conſciences) who hath ſent forth Paſtors according to his own heart, to adminiſter freely, as they have freely received, and to turn people from the darkneſs to the light: Let not a deceived heart lead you aſide, to heap up to your ſelves Teachers, that cannot profit, and ſo neglect this great ſalvation; to that of God in all your conſciences I commend theſe things, to be anſwered with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to him, that you may alſo come to have fellowſhip with us, and truly our fellowſhip is with the Father and the Son, in the light of life, which the Scripture is a witneſs of, and the true Chriſt,
<note n="q" place="margin">Col. 1.27.</note> the hope of glory (in us) we witneſs, and of him we bear teſtimony, and for that faith
<note n="r" place="margin">Jude 3.</note> which was once delivered to the Saints, which purifies the heart, do we earneſtly contend; and in humility we can ſay, that we have denyed ſelf in obedience to Chriſt, who is the reſurrection and the life, and he that is wiſe, let him turn in hither, for he that is of God heareth us, but they that are of the world heareth us not, becauſe they have not heard nor known the Father and the Son, of whom we bear teſtimony, by whoſe grace we are ſaved.</p>
            <p>And now if any among the Anabaptiſts, or any other form whatſoever have but moderation, to read this with the ſpirit and underſtanding, they may have true information, without an interpreter, wherefore they are called to ariſe, and come out of the ſtate of imperfection, and unto whom they muſt come, that they may find reſt for their ſouls, and refreſhment from Gods preſence, and let none be ſo fooliſh as to think that this doctrine will ſeduce or deceive them, for we have the mind of Chriſt, and
<note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.6.</note> we preach wiſdom among them that are perfect, and we preſs after perfection: wherefore I ſay,
<gap reason="missing" extent="4 pages">
                  <desc>〈4 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:174207:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>of truth, that you may prove all things, and hold faſt that which is good.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. S.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Ivelchecter</hi> 
                  <date>the 12 <hi>day of the</hi> 1 <hi>Moneth,</hi> 1658.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> Lamentation <hi>taken up for the Churchs of the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts by</hi> John Collens with a call, and warning <hi>for them to come out of the</hi> ſelf ſeparation, <hi>into the foot-ſteps of the flock, and to turn from the</hi> darkneſs <hi>to the</hi> true light.</head>
            <p>FRiends, you who call your ſelves Churches of Chriſt Jeſus, who have ſeparated your ſelves not having the ſpirit to lead, and ſeparate you from your uncleannes, and ſo are in the ſelf ſeparation, out of the power of God, which power maketh man willing to deny himſelf and take up the daily croſs which crucifieth him to the world, and the world to him, where ſin is nailed, and the power of God received, to reſiſt the Devil, which leads them captive at his will, who live in ſin and tranſgreſſion, which is the work of the Devil, and all them that are led by him have not received the faith, which giveth victory over him, nor have not believed the Goſpel, which is <hi>the power of God to ſalvation,</hi> nor received Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>to ſave them from their ſins</hi> which all they that do believe, do receive even <hi>power to become the ſons of God, and joynt heirs with Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Friends, in the Name and fear of the Lord God Almighty, do I warn you, and in bowels of love and tenderneſs do in Chriſts ſtead beſeech you, that in the light of Chriſt Jeſus made manifeſt, which never changeth, but bears true teſtimony for God, try and conſider, whether whilſt you <hi>live in ſin, you are not ſervants to ſin, and doth the work of the Devil: and the wages of ſin is death, and he that ſoweth to the fleſh must of the fleſh reap corruption, and he that ſoweth to the ſpirit, ſhall of the ſpirit reap life everlaſting, you cannot ſerve two masters, neither can you ſerve God and Mammon, verily verily except you be born again you cannot inherit the Kingdom of God, and he that is born of God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſin, for his ſeed remaineth in him, he that ſinneth is of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil;</hi> now friends in the cooleneſs and moderation conſider,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:174207:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:174207:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:174207:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:174207:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:174207:15"/>whether you know this birth brought forth in you which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not commit ſin, the ſeed immortal begotten of God, which enters the Kingdom of God; and try your ſelves how you ſtand in the preſence of the Lord; in ſingleneſs of heart, and deceive not your ſelves with words; <hi>for the goſpel is not in word but in power;</hi> a profeſſion of God and Chriſt will not ſave you whilſt you deny the power of God, by which ſin is crucified, <hi>for whoſoever committeth ſin is under the Law:</hi> and he was made manifeſt to take away our fins, truly a lamentation is taken up for you, <hi>how are you fallen; how are your garments defiled;</hi> how are you degenerated and fallen back to the love of the world with its cuſtomes, faſhioned and traditions, with the luſts and vanities thereof, renewing again thoſe idolatries which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly you have deſtroyed, how is your leader and great Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle amongſt you, <hi>Thomas Collier,</hi> become an enemy of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs <hi>reſiſting the holy Ghoſt: and perverting the right way of God</hi> preaching up ſin and imperfection for term of life, going about with all the ſtrength he can muſter up to eſtabliſh the kingdom of the Devil in the Church of Chriſt, raking up the failings of the Saints recorded, to confirm the reign of the man of ſin for ever, condemning the generation of the juſt, bringing in new deſtinctions to make the body of Chriſt an imperfect ſinful body, how doth be blaſphem God &amp; his tabernacle, and them that dwell in Heaven, <hi>who ſhal lay any thing to the charge of Gods elect,</hi> how doth he ſlander, reproach and falſly accuſe the innocent and harmleſs Lambs of Chriſt Jeſus, yea the Lord is witneſs between him &amp; us, <hi>and we call Heaven and earth to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt him this day,</hi> that theſe things
<note n="*" place="margin">In his book called <hi>a dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue between a miniſter and a Chriſtian.</hi>
               </note> aſſerted by him as our principles never entered into our hearts, our conſciences bearing us witneſs in the ſight of God, though he like a whore hath wiped his mouth at a looking glaſs, in which the children of light ſee much more of his deformity and wickedneſs; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving perverted the words in ſeveral books as he doth <hi>the Scriptures to his own deſtruction,</hi> and out of his miſchievous heart, hath wreſted their honeſt intents, and taken pieces of ſentences and raiſed it up a lie (out of his own wicked heart) upon them, and then overturned his own work; but that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:174207:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>which is written in thoſe books remaineth untouched by him, his own lies being but wiped from them, as any who are without prejudice may eaſily ſee, reading over the things contained in thoſe books who will ſufficiently clear them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but the Devil <hi>who was a lyer from the beginning, is now caſt out of heaven into the earth, and he hath great wrath with the woman, and the remnant of her ſeed who keep the word of God and teſtimony of Jeſus; but the arm of the Lord is ſtretched out over us, and in his fear are we preſerved from the rage of our enemies,</hi> yea <hi>a pillar of fire to give us light</hi> goeth before us, which is a cloud and darkneſs to our <hi>Egyptian</hi> like enemies that follow after us:</p>
            <p>Truly my ſoul pitties you, and my bowels hath even yerned on you, for many dayes; oh that you had an ear that you could hear, and an heart that you could underſtand: you have played the harlot and are departed from God, and you have joyned your ſelves to another beſides the Lord, <hi>you have run a whoreing after your own Inventions, and you have worſhipped the works of your hands,</hi> and your Paſtours hath deceived you, for the Lord doth not ſmile upon you, <hi>but his jealouſy burneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you as a fire,</hi> yet return and he may have mercy, and whilſt the Spirit of the Lord ſtrives, anſwer with obedience; for he hath ſaid <hi>his ſpirit ſhall not alwayes ſtrive with man,</hi> and while you have the light, believe in the light, and bring all your deeds unto the light that they may be proved and tryed, whether they be wrought in God.</p>
            <p>And now friends in the fear of the Lord deal honeſtly with your own ſelves, and let us reaſon together, and in the light of Chriſt Jeſus weigh and try all things, and ſee with the light (which will deal plainly with you) whether you are indeed ſuch as you profeſs your ſelves; and whether the ordinances you ſo much talk of be indeed the ordinances of Chriſt, or but ſhadowes, whether water baptiſm or <hi>the baptiſm of the ſpirit be the baptiſm of Chriſt,</hi> ſince <hi>there is but one baptiſm,</hi> whether you have <hi>heard the voice of Chriſt or ſeen his ſhape at any time,</hi> that hath commanded you in the particular to take up thoſe ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, or a perſwaſion in your own minds from the letter when as the letter killeth, or whether ſuch a thing as water be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the letter, or your own Imaginations from the letter.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:174207:16"/>
            <p> Whether the bread you break be the body of Chriſt, or the cup you drink be his blood, ſince it doth not cleanſe you from ſin? whether the prayers you make be in the ſpirit, and you can ſay in the preſence of the Lord, you lift up holy hands; have them that teach among you the ſpirit of infalibility, and revelation of the mind of Chriſt, or they ſpeak a devination of their own brain, and hath not received the word of the Lord from his mouth, but boaſt in anothers line, and what themſelves have invented, and whether this be the ſpirit of God, or the ſpirit of errour which is not of God; and whether the Covenant, and ordinances which doth not make the commers thereunto perfect, be not that which is to be done away as weake and unprofitable? whether your faith and preaching be not alſo vain, foraſmuch as you believe you ſhall never overcome ſin while you live, and your faith doth not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie your hearts, and ſince that as a tree falleth ſo it lyeth, and as death leaves you judgment finds you, and that there is no repentance in the grave whether you muſt goe, and that nothing that is unclean, or that worketh abomination, or that maketh a lye ſhall ever enter the City of our God.</p>
            <p>Therefore once more in the name of the Lord I warn you, come out from among them, all ye that are tender-hearted, and that deſires ſalvation to your ſoules <hi>come out from among them, and be ye ſeperate, and touch no unclean thing and I will receive you ſaith the Lord,</hi> for whoſoever cannot witneſſe Chriſt Jeſus a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour from ſin in the particular, ſhall never witneſs him a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our from condemnation, &amp; refuſe not to walk with a pure per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect people, as <hi>T.C.</hi> ſaith we be, and follow us no farther then as we follow Chriſt, for we have the mind of Chriſt; therfore own the light which convinceth you of ſin, for as living witneſſes for the name of our God do we ſtand, that the light which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinceth of ſin is the true light that leadeth out of ſin, all them that walks in the light, as he is in the light, they wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the blood of Chriſt to cleanſe from all ſin, which joyns us to Chriſt as members of his body, whereby we receive the ſpirit of the Father, to lead and guide us to do his will, which is our ſanctification, which ſpirit revealeth the Son, Chriſt Jeſus the light, who worketh all our works in us, and for us,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:174207:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>whoſe work is perfect, for we are no more our own, but bought with a price; ſo are we baptized by one ſpirit into one body, and made conformable to his death, who hath rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed us to life, glory be to his name for ever: here is the Church in God the Father, where the true Church, Ordinances and fellowſhip is known, and the true worſhip in ſpirit and in truth (in which onely the father is worſhipped) lived in; yea, and we bear teſtimony according to the Scriptures, that there is no other name given under heaven by which men can be ſaved, but by Chriſt Jeſus, who is revealed in us, our hope of glory; this is he that hath told us all that ever we have done: is not this the very Chriſt, who was in the beginning with God, whoſe day <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaw, whom the profeſſing Jews (when made manifeſt) who had the Scriptures of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets (who propheſied of him) read every Sabbath day, yet their voices they knew not, but crucified the Lord of Life, and put him to open ſhame, as it is at this day; <hi>Him hath God raiſed, and given him a name above every name, that at the name of Jeſus every knee ſhould bow;</hi> this is he whom we bear teſtimony to, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus the ſame yeſterday, to day and for ever;</hi> therefore take heed leaſt ye be found fighters againſt God, and no longer believe lyes, but caſt out the lyar from amongſt you, for the lyar is of the Devil, and whilſt you join with him, you are one with him, and muſt partake of his plagues. Therefore hear and fear before the Lord, for the <hi>Lord will rain ſnares upon the wicked and pour out ſhame and contempt upon his adverſaries;</hi> and go on ſpeedily with your promiſe which you have promiſed the Lord in your Epiſtle, That <hi>you will caſt out ſin or ſinners out of the houſe of God,</hi> ſo may the Lord have a Church free from ſin upon the earth, for he is come whoſe right it is, and the Kingdom and the Government ſhall be his, who will rule the Heathen with a rod of iron, and break them in pieces like a Potters veſſel. And now have I eaſed my ſpirit, and cleared my conſcience towards you, whether you will hear or forbear, and the Lord will be clear of you, when he cometh in ten thouſands of his Saints to execute the judgements written; <hi>this honour hath all the ſaints.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:174207:17"/>
            <p> From him who was once owned as a Brother amongſt you, and ſince owned a brother by you, whilſt walking in the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of my mind running to the ſame exceſs of riot with you; but ſince the Lord in mercy viſited me, and called me out of darkneſs, into his marvellous light, I have been hated and deſpightfully uſed by ſome of you, who am known to many of you by the name of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. C.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
